UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO SCHOOL OF MEDICINE

Drew E. Winters, PhD. drew.winters@cuanschutz.edu 317-525-3133

Biographical sketch

Drew E. Winters, PhD. is a post-doctoral fellow at the University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus In the department of Psychiatry under the Developmental Psychobiology and Behavior T32 program. His research focuses on brain and behavior mechanisms underlying neurocognitive and socio-affective processes with an emphasis on adolescents with callous-unemotional traits. In this vein, this work aims to identify replicable neural mechanisms that may improve development and testing of interventions for youth with callous-unemotional traits.

Ed

Education	
University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO.	Current
 Post-Doctoral Fellow: Developmental Psychobiology 	
Research Group (DPRG)	
- Primary mentor: Dr. Joseph Sakai, M.D.	
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN. – Ph.D.	April 2020
Indiana University, Indianapolis, IN. – MSW	May 2016
Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN. – B.S.	May 2013
Certifications	
Machine Learning Using Scikit-Learn in Python – Inira	May 2022
Data Scientist in Python - DataCamp	Nov 2021
Computational Neuroscience – Neuromatch Academy	July 2021
Data Scientist in R – DataCamp	April 2020

Academic appointments

University of Colorado	Research Analyst	2021-Present
University of Colorado	Post-Doctoral Fellow	2020-Present
Indiana University	Adjunct Professor	2017-2020
University of Michigan	Teaching Assistant	2019 & 2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Analyst	2018-2020
Indiana University SOM	Research Assistant	2016-2020
Indiana University	Research Assistant	2014-2015

Hospital, government, or other professional positions

Multilevel Modeling II Advanced Topics – EITM

Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Variables – EITM

Network Analysis II Advanced Topics – EITM

School Evaluation – Aurora, CO	Statistician	2021-Present
UCHealth Encompass program - Aurora, CO	Therapist	2020-2021
Family Works Inc Indianapolis, IN	Therapist	2016-2020
Rogers behavioral health – Skokie IL	Behavioral Therapist	2014-2016

Honors, special recognitions, and awards

Postdoctoral Association Travel Award

Oct 2020

Oct 2020

Oct 2018

University of Colorado, Aurora, CO	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery	2021
Multilevel Modeling II: Advanced Topics	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery	2021
Network Analysis II: Advanced Topics	
Empirical Implications of Theoretical Models – Statistics Mastery	2018
Structural Equation Modeling with Latent Models	
Developmental, Child, and Family Psychology Fellowship	2018
ICPSR Quantitative Methods of Social Research Ann Harbor, MI	
Indiana University Travel Fellow	2017-2019
Graduate Professional Student Government Fellowship	2016
Miranda Pang Endowment	2014
Phi Kappa Phi: Academic Honor Society	2013
Tau Upsilon Alpha: Human Services Academic Honor Society	2013
Hellen I. and Rodney E. Nern Scholarship	2013
embership in professional organizations	
Society for the Scientific Study of Daychonethy (SSSD)	2022 currer

Me

Society for the Scientific Study of Psychopathy (SSSP)	2022-current
Society of Clinical Child and Adolescent Psychology	2020-current
Society for Social Work and Research (SSWR)	2017-current

Major Committee and Service Responsibilities

Board of Directors, National Association of Alcohol and other Drugs 2011-2018 of Abuse Counselors, Indiana Chapter, Indianapolis, IN

Licensure and board certification

<u>License</u>	<u>Certified</u>	Recertified
Licensed Social Worker – Colorado	7/2020	7/2021
Licensed Social Worker – Indiana	7/2016	8/2019

Review and referee work

Emotion	Ad hoc reviewer	2022
Journal of Drug Issues	Ad hoc reviewer	2022
Brain and Behavior	Ad hoc reviewer	2022
Cerebral Cortex	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Psychophysiology	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Journal of Drug and Alcohol Dependence	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Neuroscience Letters	Ad hoc reviewer	2021
Journal of Juvenile Justice	Ad hoc reviewer	2018
Journal of Child and Family Studies	Ad hoc reviewer	2017
Mindfulness	Ad hoc reviewer	2016

Open-Source Software Packages

resmod. A python package that calculates interaction terms using centered residuals that can be used in any regression framework https://pypi.org/project/resmod/

fsub_extractor. A python package that ties brain structural for functional data together. https://github.com/smeisler/fsub_extractor

Invited extramural lectures, presentations and visiting professorships

Winters, D.E., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M., Computational Lesioning 7/2022

of Heterogenous Functional Connectomes Explains Variance in Adolescent Callous-Unemotional Traits. Neurohackadamy, University of Washington, Seattle, WA	
Sanchez, C.R., Cooley, J.L., Winters, D.E. , Ricker, B.T., & Fite, P.J. <i>Prospective associations between forms of aggression and peer victimization: The moderating role of prosocial behavior</i> . Biennial Research Conference on Relational Aggression, Virtual Conference.	7/2022
Winters, D.E. , <i>Introduction to R for medical students</i> . University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	4/2022
Winters, D.E., Cognitive Load Sensitivity Impacts Theory of Mind Impairments in Callous-Unemotional Traits. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	4/2022
Winters, D.E., Affective Theory of Mind Impairments in Youth with Callous-Unemotional Traits: The Role of Cognitive Control. American College of Neuropsychopharmacology. San Juan, PR	12/2021
Winters, D.E., Network typology of adolescents with callous- unemotional traits. Department of Psychiatry Poster Session, University of Colorado Anschutz Medical Campus, Aurora, CO	3/2021
Winters, D.E. , Adolescent Prosocial Behavior and Affective Theory of Mind: The Role of Cognitive Control and Callousness. Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	3/2021
Winters, D.E. , <i>Longitudinal Data Analysis Using Secondary Data</i> . S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	1/2021
Winters, D.E. , <i>Neural Connectivity of Empathy and its Impairments in Adolescents</i> . Developmental Psychobiology Research Group, Denver, CO	10/2020
Winters, D.E. , <i>Statistical Approaches of Propensity Score Matching</i> . Training the Indiana Department of Children Services data analysis and evaluation team, Indianapolis, IN.	3/2020
Winters, D.E., Secondary data analysis. S728 multivariate statistics, Dr. Sadaaki Fukui. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	1/2020
Winters, D.E. Mindfulness and Acceptance and Commitment Therapy in Clinical Practice. Advanced clinical practice, Dr. Vincent Starnino, instructor. Indiana University School of Social Work, Indianapolis, IN.	6/2017
Winters, D.E . <i>Mindfulness in Addictions Treatment</i> . Presentation to staff and clients at the Life Recovery Center, Indianapolis, IN.	8/2016
Winters, D.E . <i>Mindfulness in Clinician Self-Care, and Clinical Practice</i> . Presented to the staff and honor society recipients of Chi Eta Sigma for marriage and family therapist. Purdue University, Fort Wayne, IN.	4/2016

Teaching record

 ${\bf Indiana\ University\ School\ of\ Social\ Work-Teaching\ Assistant}$

S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar S623 Practice Research Integrative Seminar	Online Online Seminar	Summer 2017 Spring 2017 Fall 2016
University of Michigan – ICPSR Regression Analysis II: Linear models Regression Analysis II: Linear models	Online Seminar	Summer 2020 Summer 2019
Indiana University – Adjunct Professor S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab S728 Advanced Statistics – Statistics Lab S718 Intermediate Statistics – Statistics Lab S517 Assessment in Mental Health & Addictions	Seminar Seminar Seminar Seminar	Spring 2020 Fall 2019 Spring 2019 Fall 2018 Summer 2018
Mentoring Neuromatch Academy – Computational Neuroscience N I mentored a group of five participants in the coneuroscience track on completing capstone proj	mputational	2022
Gabriel Yepes, M.D. – Research Mentor - I mentored Dr. Yepes on conducting research as manuscripts resulting in one research publication	nd writing	2021
Grant support Developmental Psychobiology Endowment Fund. Projection of cognitive load on prosocial behavior amongst adolescents with high callous-unemotional traits and type developing controls.' Funding amount \$7,220 Role: PI	early	2021-2022
National Institutes of Mental Health T32MH015442-42; Laudenslager, Mark (PI), Developmental Psychopatholo Psychobiology & Behavior. <u>Role</u> : Postdoctoral Fellow		2020 - present
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Pierce, Barbra (PI), Indiana University Medicine. Role: Research Analyst		2019 - 2020
Indiana Department of Children Services Title IV-E Wa 13-4F-C0-0981; Hall, Jim (PI), Indiana University Scho Medicine. Role: Research Assistant		2017 - 2019

Bibliography

Published

Published Peer-Reviewed Articles

- **Winters, D. E.**, Hyde, L. W. (2022). Shared Functional Network Connectivity Between Callous-Unemotionality and both Cognitive and Affective Empathy. *Journal of Affective Disorders*.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Pruitt P. J., Damoiseaux J.S, Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effect of CU traits on functional connectivity underlying empathy in adolescents. *Psychiatry Research Neuroimaging*. Doi: 10.1016/j.pscychresns.2021.111429

- **Winters D.E.**, Sakai, J.T., Carston, R.M. (2021) Resting-state network topology characterizing callous-unemotional traits in adolescence. Neuroimage: Clinical, 2021: p. 102878.
- **Winters, D.E.,** Susan M., Hopfer, C., Sakai, J.T. (2021). Moderating effects of CU traits on transdiagnostic symptoms association with suicidality in adolescents. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01256-w
- Winters D.E., Pruitt P. J., Fukui S., Cyders M.A., Pierce B. J., Lay K., Damoiseaux J.S. (2021). Indirect paths between functional connectivity underlying heterogenous depression symptoms in adolescents via cognitive and affective empathy. *Child Psychiatry and Human Development*. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10578-021-01242-2
- Winters, D.E., Pruit P.J., Fukui, S., Cyders, M. A., Pierce, B. J., Lay, K., Damoiseaux, J. S. (2021). Network functional connectivity underlying dissociable cognitive and affective components of empathy in adolescence. *Neuropsychologia*. 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2021.107832
- **Winters, D.E.**, Brandon-Friedman, R., Yepes, G., Hinkley, J. (2020). Systematic review and meta-analysis of socio-cognitive and socio-affective processes association with adolescent substance use. *Drug and Alcohol Dependence*. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2020.108479
- **Winters, D.E.**, Pierce, B. J., Imburgia, T. (2020) Concrete services usage on child placement stability: Propensity score matched effects. *Child and Youth Service Review*. DOI: 10.1016/j.childyouth.2020.105362
- **Winters, D.E.**, Wu, W., Fukui, S. (2020). Longitudinal effects of cognitive and affective empathy on adolescent substance use. *Substance Use & Misuse*, 1-7. DOI: 10.1080/10826084.2020.1717537
- Winters, D.E., Fukui, S., Leibenluft, E., Hulvershorn L.A., (2018). Improvements in Irritability with Open-Label Methylphenidate in Youth with Comorbid Attention Deficit/Hyperactivity Disorder and Disruptive Mood Dysregulation Disorder. *Journal of Child and Adolescent Psychopharmacology*, 28(5): 298-305.
- Beerbower, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Kondrat, D. (2018). Bio-psycho-social-spiritual needs of adolescents and young adults with life-threatening illnesses: Implications for social work practice. *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-17. DOI: 10.1080/00981389.2018.1430091
- Winters, D.E., Beerbower, E. (2017). Mindfulness and Meditation as an Adjunctive Treatment for Adolescents Involved in the Juvenile Justice System: Is Repairing the Brain and Nervous System Possible? *Social Work in Health Care*, 1-21. Doi:10.1080/00981389.2017.1316341

Published Book Chapters

Armstrong, E., **Winters, D.E.**, Jaggers, J. (2018). Mental Health in Prison Populations. Serving the Stigmatized: Working within the Incarcerated Environment. W.T. Church and D.W. Springer, Oxford University Press.

Technical Reports for the State of Indiana

Winters, D.E., Imburgia, T., Pierce, B. J. (2017, 2018, 2019, 2020). Concrete Services Spending and outcomes for youth. Indiana Department of Child Services Child Welfare Title IV-E Waiver Demonstration Project Extension: Final Report.

Unpublished

- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Affective theory of mind impairments underlying callous-unemotional traits and the role of cognitive control: A pilot study.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Massey, S.H., Sakai, J.T. (under review). Adolescent substance use outcomes in response to social consequences of use: the role of empathy.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review). Prosocial behavior limitations associated with callous-unemotional traits are moderated by internalizing symptoms
- Sakai, J.T., Chintaluru, Y., Raymond, K., McWilliams, S., Carter, R., **Winters, D.E.**, Mikulich, S. (under review). Can Moral Elevation Response Increase Prosocial Behavior? Examining the Effects of Psychopathic Traits.
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. (under review) Callous-Unemotional traits association with prosocial behavior and the mediating role of cognitive control.
- **Winters, D. E.**, Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. (under review) Resting-state connectivity underlying cognitive control's association with perspective taking in callous-unemotional traits.

In preparation

- Winters, D. E., Leopold, D.R., Sakai, J.T., Carter, R.M. Efficiency of heterogenous functional connectomes explains variance in callous-unemotional traits after computational lesioning cortical midline and salience regions
- **Winters, D.E.**, Sakai, J.T. Cognitive processes underlying prosocial decision making in callous-unemotional traits.